Trees are more than just landscaping in
Southwest Florida. They're part of our
region's identity. And after a rare
winter freeze followed by persistent
drought, local growers say their crops
are taking a major hit this year. Wink
News reporter Bridget Buchalski talks to
a local farm palm farm where recovery is
slow and costly.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, a palm tree isn't supposed to
sound like that.
>> We were hoping to really start selling a
lot of these, but this, you know,
basically took the wind out of our
sales.
>> Gene McAvoy runs A1 Palms, and right now
things are a struggle.
>> It's going to take a good year, and
maybe even 2 years before they grow back
out and are sellable because people buy
them for their aesthetic beauty, not for
looking like they're brown and dead.
>> This winter freeze hit hard.
>> cannot take the real cold temperatures
that we experienced this winter, and you
can see most of the leaves have had been
frozen.
>> Across the industry, McAvoy says some
growers lost 75% of their palms.
>> You know, the full extent of the damage
was apparent. Anything that was under
about 6 ft, which I'm 6 ft,
was killed dead.
>> Now that the freeze is over, these palms
are working on bouncing back, and that
means shedding their dead fronds like
this one right here. But the thing is,
the more brown fronds they have, the
longer it's going to take to be all
green again.
>> Palm trees don't make a lot of leaves
every year. They only make five or six,
seven leaves a year.
>> Recovery is slow, and now a new problem,
drought.
>> It slows them down. But when we
fertilize them, when it's dry like this,
the fertilizer doesn't do much because
it takes the rain to wash it into the
soil and get it into the trees.
>> So everything takes longer, but McAvoy
says it's not the time to stop.
>> This whole area we're cleaning up. We're
going to plant some new trees, and if
you're going to be in the palm tree
business, you have to have palm trees.
>> In LaBelle, Bridget Buchalski, Wink
News.